<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10224290</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2193067</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Role of the Scavenger Receptor MARCO in Alveolar Macrophage Binding of Unopsonized Environmental Particles </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palecanda</surname><given-names>Aiyappa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paulauskis</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Mutairi</surname><given-names>Eiman</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Imrich</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Guozhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Hiroshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>Tatsuhiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>Karl</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x02016;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koziel</surname><given-names>Henry</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x000b6;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kobzik</surname><given-names>Lester</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">&#x02021;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1bfeb00N0x2029410">From the <label>&#x0002a;</label>Physiology Program, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, Massachusetts 02115; the  <label>&#x02021;</label>Department of Pathology, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts 02115; the  <label>&#x000a7;</label>Department of Molecular Biology and Medicine, Research Center for Advanced Science and  Technology, University of &#x02009;Tokyo, Tokyo 153, &#x02009;Japan; the <label>&#x02016;</label>Department of Medical Biochemistry and  Biophysics, Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden; and the <label>&#x000b6;</label>Department of Medicine, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts 02215</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Lester Kobzik, Physiology Program, Harvard School of Public Health, 665  Huntington Ave., Boston, MA 02115. Phone: 617-432-2247; Fax: 617-432-0014; E-mail: <email>lkobzik&#x00040;hsph.harvard.edu</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>189</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>1506</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>1999</year></date></history><copyright-year>1999</copyright-year><abstract><p>Alveolar macrophages (AMs) avidly bind and ingest unopsonized environmental particles and  bacteria through scavenger-type receptors (SRs). AMs from mice with a genetic deletion of the  major macrophage SR (types AI and AII; SR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>) showed no decrease in particle binding compared with SR<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup> mice, suggesting that other SRs are involved. To identify these receptors,  we generated a monoclonal antibody (mAb), PAL-1, that inhibits hamster AM binding of unopsonized particles (TiO<sub>2</sub>, Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, and latex beads; 66 &#x000b1; 5, 77 &#x000b1; 2, and 85 &#x000b1; 2% inhibition, respectively, measured by flow cytometry). This antibody identifies a protein of &#x0223c;70 kD on the  AM surface (immunoprecipitation) that is expressed by AMs and other macrophages in situ. A  cDNA clone encoding the mAb PAL-1&#x02013;reactive protein isolated by means of COS cell expression was found to be 84 and 77% homologous to mouse and human scavenger receptor  MARCO mRNA, respectively. Transfection of COS cells with MARCO cDNA conferred  mAb-inhibitable TiO<sub>2</sub> binding. Hamster MARCO also mediates AM binding of unopsonized  bacteria (67 &#x000b1; 5 and 47 &#x000b1; 4% inhibition of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> binding by  mAb PAL-1). A polyclonal antibody to human MARCO identified the expected &#x0223c;70-kD  band on Western blots of lysates of normal bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) cells (&#x0003e;90% AMs)  and showed strong immunolabeling of human AMs in BAL cytocentrifuge preparations and  within lung tissue specimens. In normal mouse AMs, the anti-MARCO mAb ED31 also  showed immunoreactivity and inhibited binding of unopsonized particles (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub> &#x0223c;40%)  and bacteria. The novel function of binding unopsonized environmental dusts and pathogens  suggests an important role for MARCO in the lungs' response to inhaled particles.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>MARCO</kwd><kwd>alveolar</kwd><kwd>macrophage</kwd><kwd>unopsonized</kwd><kwd>environmental particle</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Normal breathing inevitably results in deep penetration  into the lungs of various environmental particles and  microorganisms. The alveolar macrophage (AM)<sup>1</sup> is the cell  that is primarily responsible for the binding, ingestion, and,  ultimately, clearance of inhaled particulate matter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). If  inhaled microorganisms are opsonized by antibodies and/or  complement, AMs can bind and phagocytose them via Fc  and C receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). AMs more frequently encounter various unopsonized environmental particles that they nevertheless bind and ingest with remarkable avidity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). The  AM response to inhaled particles ranges from abundant production of inflammatory cytokines and reactive oxygen intermediates to simple ingestion and clearance with minimal  inflammation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). The latter capacity is especially useful  for clearance of inert dusts and particles without risk of the  potentially damaging effects of an unnecessary inflammatory  response. Thus, receptor-mediated binding of inhaled particles and modulation of AM activation are important first  steps in the maintenance of lung homeostasis.</p><p>Previous work in our laboratory identified a role for  scavenger-type receptor(s) in this process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). The scavenger receptors (SRs) are characterized by high-affinity binding of a relatively broad array of ligands such as modified  LDL, some (but not all) polynucleotides and polysaccharides, and bacterial endotoxin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). There are three  classes of SRs, A, B, and C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). The two class A SRs, type I  and type II, are homotrimeric glycoproteins composed of  three 77-kD monomers generated from alternative splicing  of a message encoded by a single gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). SR-As are  abundant on monocytes and tissue macrophages as well  as other cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). A recently identified SR-A,  MARCO, also binds acetylated LDL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). MARCO,  like SR-A, binds bacteria but not yeast and is expressed on  peritoneal macrophages and splenic marginal zone macrophages but has not been found in the lung (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>The SR ligand polyinosinic acid (PI) caused a marked inhibition of AM binding of oxide particles, latex beads, fly ash,  and particles collected from ambient air (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). PI also inhibited the uptake of quartz particles (SiO<sub>2</sub>) by AMs in vivo  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). These data suggested that SR-like receptors mediate  nonopsonic phagocytosis of pollutant particles. Although  SR-A (I/II) seemed the most likely candidate, the use of &#x02009;PI  precluded precise identification of receptor(s), as this reagent  can inhibit more than one member of the SR family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>).</p><p>In the studies reported here, we found that SR-A&#x02013;deficient AMs exhibited normal (comparable to wild-type)  ability to bind particles both in vitro and in vivo. To identify other scavenger-type receptors involved, we developed  an mAb capable of blocking hamster AM particle binding.  Using this mAb, we performed expression cloning for the  receptor, which is similar to mouse and human MARCO  in cDNA sequence homology and binding of bacteria. We  also show that mouse and human AMs express MARCO  and that mouse MARCO is involved in binding of unopsonized particles. The results indicate that MARCO is  likely to play an important role in the initial responses to  inhaled particles in the lung.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec disp-level="3"><title>Reagents and Particles.</title><p>TiO<sub>2</sub> and Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> were provided by Dr.  J. Brain (Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, MA). These  particles have been shown to be heterogeneous in size, with a  median diameter of 1.3 &#x003bc;m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Latex beads (1.0 &#x003bc;m in diameter; sulfated polystyrene) that show green fluorescence after excitation at 488 nm were obtained from Interfacial Dynamics Co.  All particles were suspended in balanced salt solution (BSS<sup>&#x02212;</sup> [124  mM NaCl, 5.8 mM KCl, 10 mM dextrose, and 20 mM Hepes])  as stock solutions and sonicated &#x0223c;30 s before use. Anti-TNP  (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pharmingen">PharMingen</named-content>), anti-heparan sulfate mAbs (Seikagaku Corp.), anti&#x02013; human &#x003b2;2 microglobulin mAb (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pharmingen">PharMingen</named-content>), and a nonspecific  rat IgG1 (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pharmingen">PharMingen</named-content>) were used as isotype-matched controls.  The anti&#x02013;human MARCO antibody was raised in rabbits as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). The anti&#x02013;mouse MARCO mAb, ED31 (IgG1), was  provided by Dr. G. Kraal (Vrije Universiteit, Amsterdam, The  Netherlands) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). All reagents not otherwise specified were obtained from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content></p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Cell Isolation and Flow Cytometric Assay of Particulate Binding.</title><p>SR-A&#x02013;deficient mice were prepared as reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Mice or  hamsters were killed by intraperitoneal pentobarbital injection.  AMs obtained by repeated lung lavage with BSS<sup>&#x02212;</sup> were centrifuged at 150 <italic>g</italic> and resuspended in BSS<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>. AMs (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> in 100 &#x003bc;l  BSS<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>) were preincubated with mAbs (100 &#x003bc;l hybridoma supernatant or 10 &#x003bc;g/ml mAb) or inhibitors (10 &#x003bc;g/ml) and 2.5 &#x003bc;g/ml cytochalasin D for 5 min on ice in a 1-ml microfuge tube. After the  addition of probe sonicated particles or beads, the tubes were rotated at 37&#x000b0;C for 30 min, placed on ice, and analyzed by flow cytometry. Flow cytometry was performed using an Ortho 2150  cytofluorograph as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). AM uptake of particles was measured using the increase in the mean right angle scatter (RAS) caused by these granular materials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). Latex bead  binding is expressed as relative fluorescence.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Assay of Bacteria Binding.</title><p>Fluorescent-labeled, heat-killed bacteria (<italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>) and yeast (Zymosan)  were purchased from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pharmingen">PharMingen</named-content>. The bacteria binding assay  was performed exactly as described above, except that AMs were  incubated with either bacteria (5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup>) or yeast (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>) instead  of particles. Binding was measured by detecting AM-associated  fluorescence by flow cytometry.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>In Vivo Particle Uptake.</title><p>Mice were anaesthetized with halothane (4%), and 125 &#x003bc;l TiO<sub>2</sub> (50 &#x003bc;g/ml) in BSS<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> was instilled  into the lungs using a 22-gauge canula. Bronchoalveolar lavage  (BAL) was performed 30 min after instillation, and aliquots of  BAL were immediately analyzed by flow cytometry to quantitate cell-associated particles.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Production of mAb.</title><p>BALB/c mice were immunized by intraperitoneal injection of 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> hamster AMs. After 3 wk, mice received another injection of 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> AMs i.p., and 3 d later, spleens of  the mice were removed. The splenocytes were fused with a nonsecreting mouse myeloma, P3U1, using polyethylene glycol 4000 and  cultured in DMEM containing hypoxanthine, aminopterin, and thymidine. After 2 wk, supernatants from hybridoma cultures were  screened for their ability to inhibit the adhesion of TiO<sub>2</sub> to AMs.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Immunoprecipitation.</title><p>Hamster AM cell surface proteins were labeled with sulfo-NHS-LC-biotin (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pierce">Pierce Chemical Co.</named-content>) as per the  manufacturer's suggested protocol and resuspended at a concentration of 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> cells/ml in a 1% extraction buffer (1% Triton X-100,  50 mM Tris-HCl, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and  5 mM iodoacetamide supplemented with 40 &#x003bc;g/ml PMSF, 2 &#x003bc;g/ml  aprotinin, and 10 &#x003bc;g/ml phenanthroline as protease inhibitors). The  lysates were precleared with rat anti&#x02013;mouse IgM magnetic beads  (Dynabeads<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>; <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="Dynal">Dynal Inc.</named-content>). Aliquots of lysate were incubated with  mAbs PAL-1 or RP-3 bound to rat anti&#x02013;mouse IgM magnetic  beads overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. The immunoprecipitates were washed in  cold lysis buffer (without protease inhibitors), subjected to SDS-PAGE, electroblotted to membrane filters, probed with avidin&#x02013; HRP conjugate (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pierce">Pierce Chemical Co.</named-content>), and developed using  chemiluminence reagent (Supersignal<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> ; <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pierce">Pierce Chemical Co.</named-content>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Immunohistochemistry.</title><p>Cryostat sections of hamster tissues were  fixed in buffered 2% paraformaldehyde for 10 min, followed by  10 min in 100% cold (&#x02212;20&#x000b0;C) methanol. After rinsing, immunostaining was performed by sequential application of primary  antibody (mAb PAL-1 [5 &#x003bc;g/ml] or anti-heparan sulfate mAb  [5 &#x003bc;g/ml], goat anti&#x02013;mouse IgG [1:50; Sternberger Monoclonals,  Inc.], and mouse peroxidase&#x02013;antiperoxidase complex [1:100;  Sternberger Monoclonals, Inc.]), followed by labeling with chromogen diaminobenzidine and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. To increase sensitivity, an additional cycle of secondary and peroxidase&#x02013;antiperoxidase complex  was applied to sections, followed by a second chromogen reaction.  Paraffin sections of human lung tissue were immunostained using  an avidin&#x02013;biotin complex protocol as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>).  The slides were washed with water, counterstained with hematoxylin, dehydrated, and mounted for light microscopy.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Expression Cloning.</title><p>A hamster AM cDNA library prepared in  the pcDM8 vector (provided by Dr. B. Seed, Harvard Medical  School, Boston, MA; Paulauskis, J., unpublished data) was divided into small pools and transfected into COS cells. The transiently transfected COS cells were isolated by &#x0201c;panning&#x0201d; on mAb  PAL-1&#x02013;coated plates, and plasmid DNA was reisolated and amplified as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). A receptor-positive pool was identified  by PAL-1 immunostaining of transfected COS cells after six  rounds of screening. This pool was subdivided repeatedly until  we obtained a single functional plasmid that upon transfection  conferred mAb PAL-1 reactivity to COS cells. Both strands of  the cDNA insert were sequenced at the Harvard University  Biopolymers Laboratory.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Western Blot Analysis.</title><p>Human AMs were collected by BAL  from healthy adults under an institutionally reviewed and approved protocol. AMs were washed and lysates prepared as described above (see <italic>Immunoprecipitation</italic>). The lysates were mixed  with 6&#x000d7; reducing or nonreducing SDS&#x02013;solubilization buffer,  subjected to SDS-PAGE, electroblotted to membrane filters,  probed with either control rabbit IgG or purified rabbit anti&#x02013;human  MARCO antibody followed by avidin&#x02013;HRP conjugate (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pierce">Pierce  Chemical Co.</named-content>), and developed using chemiluminence reagent  (Supersignal<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> ; <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pierce">Pierce Chemical</named-content> Co).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Statistics.</title><p>Data were analyzed using ANOVA and paired <italic>t</italic> test  components of a statistical software package (Statview; Abacus  Concepts). Significance was accepted when <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="4"><title>SR-A&#x02013;deficient AMs Bind Unopsonized Particles.</title><p>To determine whether SR-A (I/II) receptors mediate AM  binding of unopsonized particles, the binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> by  SR-A (I/II)&#x02013;deficient AMs (SR-A<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>) was tested and compared with the binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> by AMs from wild-type  mice (SR-A<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup>). Microscopic evaluation of treated AMs  showed similar robust binding of TiO<sub>2 </sub>by both SR-A<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>  and SR-A<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup> AMs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> A). Quantitation by flow cytometric analysis of RAS increases showed that SR-A<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>and  SR-A<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup> AMs demonstrated essentially identical particle  binding (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> B). SR-A<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> AMs also bound unopsonized  ferric oxide and fluorescent latex beads with comparable  avidity (data not shown). The SR ligand PI inhibited the  adhesion of TiO<sub>2</sub> to both SR-A<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and SR<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup> AMs by 59 &#x000b1;  1% and 58 &#x000b1; 4%, respectively. The control polyanion,  chondroitin sulfate (CS), had no effect on particle adhesion.  To determine if the in vitro particle binding reflected in vivo  events, we measured particle binding to AMs after intratracheal instillation of TiO<sub>2</sub>. SR-A&#x02013;deficient or wild-type mice  were instilled with buffer alone or buffer containing TiO<sub>2</sub>.  After 30 min, mice were killed, BAL performed, and AM  uptake of TiO<sub>2</sub> quantified by flow cytometry. As shown in  Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> C, both SR-A&#x02013;deficient AMs and wild-type AMs  bound TiO<sub>2</sub> in vivo to a comparable degree. Thus, SR-A  deficiency does not alter unopsonized particle binding by  AMs. These results suggested that SRs other than SR-A are  involved in unopsonized particle binding to AMs. </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Effect of mAb PAL-1 on AM Binding of Particles.</title><p>To develop an mAb to the receptor that mediates particle binding, mice were immunized with hamster AMs, and hybridomas were prepared and screened for mAbs that block AM  binding of TiO<sub>2</sub>. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>), the scavenger receptor ligand, PI, blocked AM  binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> and served as a positive control for these  assays. A new mAb, PAL-1, inhibited AM binding of TiO<sub>2</sub>  by 67 &#x000b1; 5% (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 10). An isotype-matched control mAb  (anti-TNP) had no effect on AM binding of TiO<sub>2</sub>. We  next examined the effect of mAb PAL-1 on AM binding of  other environmental particles such as Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> or quartz  (SiO<sub>2</sub>) and the surrogate particle, latex beads. As shown in  Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>, PAL-1 inhibited AM binding of Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiO<sub>2,</sub> and  latex beads by 78 &#x000b1; 2, 52 &#x000b1; 24, and 85 &#x000b1; 4%, respectively.  Thus, mAb PAL-1 substantially inhibits AM binding of a  broad range of particles.  </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Immunoprecipitation of a Cell Surface Protein by mAb PAL-1.</title><p>To identify the protein(s) recognized by mAb PAL-1, immunoprecipitation experiments were carried out. AMs  were surface-labeled by sulfo-NHS-biotin (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pierce">Pierce Chemical  Co.</named-content>), and the cell surface molecules bound by PAL-1 were  analyzed by SDS-PAGE (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In both reducing and  nonreducing conditions, a single band with an apparent  molecular mass of &#x02009;70 kD was detected in lysates of normal  AMs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). This band was absent from cells precipitated  with an isotype-matched (IgM) negative control antibody. </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Tissue Localization of the PAL-1 Antigen.</title><p> Immunostaining of frozen sections from a range of normal hamster tissues with PAL-1 showed that it reacted strongly with most  or all AMs, macrophages of lymph node sinuses, and von  Kupffer cells of the liver (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> A). Macrophages in other  sites were also positive (e.g., splenic red pulp, intestinal  Peyer's patch, thymus). Cross-reactions with other tissue  structures such as endothelial cells were not observed; numerous other nonlymphoid tissues were negative (skin, brain,  heart, stomach, prostate, and kidney; data not shown).  Flow cytometric analysis showed that PAL-1 staining is detected on AMs. Lymphocytes isolated from different lymph  nodes and thymocytes were negative (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> B). Peritoneal  macrophages, neutrophils, and monocytes were predominantly negative (data not shown). </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Expression Cloning of the Particle Adhesion Receptor.</title><p> An  expression cloning protocol was used to identify the receptor mediating AM binding of particles. When transfected  into COS cells, a cDNA clone conferred mAb PAL-1 reactivity (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, A and B). Both strands of the 1.6-kb insert  were sequenced. The sequence, including part of the 5&#x02032;-  and 3&#x02032;-untranslated regions, is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> A. From the  first ATG, we predict an open reading frame of 1452 bp,  which yields a protein of 483 amino acid residues with a  predicted molecular mass of 49.5 kD. GenBank searches of  the nucleotide and protein sequences revealed significant  homology to murine and human MARCO (84 and 77%  nucleotide identity with mouse and human MARCO cDNA,  respectively; 18, 19). We refer to this clone as hamster  MARCO. Amino acid identity between hamster, murine,  and human MARCO was 77 and 65%, respectively (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> B). As shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TII">II</xref>, amino acid identity between  hamster, mouse, and human MARCO was highest in the  collagenous domain. The intracellular domain had 80%  identity between hamster and mouse MARCO, as compared with 50% identity between hamster and human  MARCO. Hamster MARCO, like human MARCO, does  not have a cysteine residue in the spacer domain, but like  mouse MARCO, it retains two cysteines in the cytoplasmic  domain. The two potential carbohydrate attachment sites in  the spacer domain, the interruption of Gly-Xaa-Yaa repeats  in the collagenous domain, and all six cysteine residues in  the scavenger receptor cysteine-rich domain (SRCR) are  conserved between all three species (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> B). Hamster  MARCO differs from both murine and human MARCO in  containing a shorter collagenous domain (237 amino acids).   </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>MARCO Expression Confers mAb PAL-1&#x02013;inhibitable TiO<sub>2  </sub>Binding to COS Cells.</title><p>To confirm the role of MARCO  in particle binding, we transfected COS cells with hamster  MARCO cDNA. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> C, COS cells transfected with MARCO cDNA bound TiO<sub>2</sub> (4.6-fold increase in RAS). TiO<sub>2</sub> binding by MARCO-transfected  COS cells but not untransfected COS cells was significantly  inhibited by the anti-MARCO mAb PAL-1 (47 &#x000b1; 6% inhibition; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> C). Controls, including untransfected COS  cells and COS cells transfected with a plasmid encoding the  cDNA for hamster CD44, exhibited binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> that  was inhibited by both PI and heparin (an agent that does  not inhibit AM binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> [10]) but not mAb PAL-1  (data not shown). The constitutive heparin-sensitive particle-binding receptor on COS cells is different from  MARCO and remains to be identified (see Discussion).</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Hamster MARCO Mediates AM Binding of Bacteria.</title><p>To  further investigate the range of ligands for hamster MARCO,  we tested the effect of mAb PAL-1 on AM binding of unopsonized microorganisms. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, mAb PAL-1  inhibited AM binding of <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> by 67 &#x000b1; 5%  and 47 &#x000b1; 4%, respectively. PAL-1 had no effect on AM  binding of Zymosan. An isotype-matched control antibody  did not inhibit bacteria and yeast binding. Thus hamster  MARCO, like human and mouse MARCO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), mediates AM binding of bacteria but not yeast. </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Expression of MARCO on Human Cells.</title><p>The original  report of human MARCO did not detect MARCO expression in the lungs of a limited number of perinatal autopsy specimens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). To evaluate whether adult human  AMs express MARCO, we performed immunologic analysis using a polyclonal antibody to a peptide from domain V  of human MARCO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Histochemical analysis of human BAL cells (&#x0003e;90% AMs) and lung tissue showed that  the anti-MARCO antibody detects antigen on AMs but  not on other cells or surrounding tissue structures (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>,  A&#x02013;D). We prepared lysates from human AMs (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 5) and  performed SDS/Western blot analysis. The anti&#x02013;human  MARCO antibody reacted specifically with a discrete band  in all AM lysates, which ran at a relative molecular mass of  &#x0223c;70 kD (results from two samples are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> E).  No reactivity was seen with an irrelevant control antibody.  The same pattern was repeated when the analysis was performed in nonreducing conditions (data not shown). Thus,  adult human AMs express MARCO. </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>SR-A&#x02013;deficient AM Binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> Is Inhibited by an Antibody to MARCO.</title><p>An mAb to mouse MARCO has been  shown to block bacteria binding by mouse macrophages  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Although expression of MARCO was not detected in  mouse lungs in the original report, we found significant immunostaining (albeit weaker than that seen in human and  hamster AMs) of normal mouse AMs by the anti-MARCO  mAb ED31 (data not shown; see Discussion) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). We therefore examined whether ED31 would block TiO<sub>2</sub> binding by  mouse AMs. In these experiments, the SR inhibitor, PI, reduced TiO<sub>2</sub> binding by 44 &#x000b1; 12 and 52 &#x000b1; 11% in SR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>  and SR<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup> mice, respectively; the control polyanion CS had  no significant effect (<italic>n</italic> &#x02265; 3). Treatment of SR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> AMs with  ED31 blocked binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> by 40 &#x000b1; 11% (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 4). TiO<sub>2  </sub>binding by SR<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup> was also inhibited by anti-MARCO mAb  treatment by 25 &#x000b1; 4% (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3). Control IgG1 had no effect  on binding. Similar inhibition of mouse AM binding of unopsonized fluorescent latex beads and bacteria was seen (data  not shown). Thus, MARCO also functions to bind environmental particles and bacteria in mouse AMs.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we have identified MARCO as a major receptor on AMs for binding of unopsonized environmental  particles and certain microorganisms. The lung is constantly  exposed to environmental substances such as microbes,  pollutant particles, and allergens. The levels of ambient air  particles in the environment have been correlated with increased morbidity and mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The clearance of  inhaled particulate matter is primarily mediated by AMs  through the process of phagocytosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). AMs have been  previously shown to avidly phagocytose unopsonized particles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). However, the receptors on the AMs that recognize and bind particles are not known. Here we have generated an mAb, PAL-1, that blocked particle and bacteria  binding by AMs. Using mAb PAL-1 as a probe, we have  cloned the cDNA encoding for the receptor from an AM  cDNA library. Transfection of COS cells conferred mAb  PAL-1 reactivity and mAb PAL-1&#x02013;inhibitable binding of  TiO<sub>2</sub>. By sequence homology and functional similarity, we  conclude that the receptor is the hamster homologue of  MARCO.</p><p>The recognition of phagocytic targets is mediated by  specific receptors on the phagocytes that either recognize  serum components (opsonins) bound to the particle or directly recognize molecular determinants on the target.  Thus, based on the mechanism of particle recognition,  phagocytosis is either opsonin-dependent or opsonin-independent. The best characterized opsonin-dependent phagocytosis receptors are the Fc&#x003b3; receptor and the complement  receptor CR3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Recent advances have highlighted  the significance of other receptors, such as the collectin receptor, C1q, in opsonin-dependent phagocytosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>).  The opsonin-independent recognition of microorganisms  and apoptotic cells is mediated by receptors such as the  scavenger receptor, mannose receptor, vitronectin receptor, asialoglycoprotein receptor, and the &#x003b2;2 integrins (35&#x02013; 37). Based on the high expression of SRs on macrophages  and their broad specificity, we considered this class of  receptors as likely suspects for interaction with inhaled  particles. Indeed, we found that AM phagocytosis of unopsonized environmental dusts (TiO<sub>2</sub>, Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiO<sub>2</sub>) or fluorescent latex beads is strongly inhibited by the SR blocker,  PI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). To more precisely determine the role of SR-A in  this interaction, we examined the ability of AMs from SR-A  (I/II)&#x02013;deficient mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>) to bind particles. We showed  that both wild-type and SR-A&#x02013;deficient macrophages  bound unopsonized TiO<sub>2</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, and latex beads  essentially identically (data not shown). The scavenger  receptor ligand PI inhibited the binding of particles to  SR-A&#x02013;deficient macrophages, suggesting that AMs express  additional SR-like molecules that mediate opsonin-independent phagocytosis of particulate matter. To identify this  receptor, we generated a monoclonal antibody, PAL-1,  which blocked AM binding of particles (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>).  Using this antibody, we have cloned the cDNA encoding  this receptor. Transfection of COS cells with this cDNA  clone confers mAb PAL-1 reactivity (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> A). Importantly, transfection confers PAL-1&#x02013;inhibitable binding of  TiO<sub>2</sub> by COS cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> C).</p><p>Interpretation of the COS cell transfection experiments  was complicated by the observation that COS cells constitutively bind particles to a substantial degree. This indicated  the presence of endogenous particle adhesion receptor(s).  However, transfection of COS cells with MARCO but not  control plasmid or cDNA resulted in mAb PAL-1&#x02013;inhibitable particle binding (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> C). Importantly, the constitutive COS cell receptor(s) for particles is sensitive to heparin  inhibition, whereas AM receptor&#x02013;mediated particle binding is not heparin sensitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Interestingly, transfection  with MARCO, in addition to conferring mAb PAL-1&#x02013;inhibitable particle binding, substantially diminished the component  that was heparin inhibitable (data not shown). We speculate that the transfected cDNA competes with the endogenous COS cell particle receptor(s) for either surface expression or binding function. Existence of a particle-binding  receptor on nonphagocytes such as COS cells is not unprecedented. The lung epithelial cell line A549 binds and  ingests unopsonized TiO<sub>2</sub>, and this binding can also be inhibited by PI and heparin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>).</p><p>The particle-binding receptor on hamster AMs is similar  to murine and human MARCO (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Murine MARCO  was originally identified by screening a murine macrophage  cDNA library with a human type XIII collagen probe.  Murine MARCO is a 210-kD trimer made up of three disulfide-linked, 52-kD monomers and is expressed only on  macrophages in spleen and lymph nodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Human  MARCO was recently cloned by screening human liver  and spleen cDNA libraries with a murine MARCO probe  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Human MARCO shares 68% sequence identity with  mouse MARCO. Hamster MARCO had higher sequence  identity to mouse than to human MARCO across all domains (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TII">II</xref>). Interestingly, hamster MARCO has a  shorter collagenous domain (less 34 amino acids) than both  human and mouse MARCO. Also, like human MARCO,  hamster MARCO does not have a cysteine residue in the  spacer domain. The six cysteines in the cysteine-rich domain  are conserved in all three species (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). The cysteine-rich  domain defines a recently identified family of proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>).  The true function of the SRCR is not clear. Hamster  MARCO, like mouse and human MARCO, binds bacteria  but not yeast (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>; references <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>The expression of MARCO on normal AMs merits discussion. Initially, both human and mouse MARCO were  not detected in normal lung (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Using Western blot  and immunolabeling techniques, we detected MARCO  expression in normal lavaged AMs and AMs presented in  diseased lungs (surgical specimens) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). The use of  adult AMs may explain the difference between this finding  and the absence of mRNA in neonatal lungs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). In  mouse AMs, we have detected faint but reproducible immunoperoxidase labeling, using mAb ED31, of normal  BAL AMs. This antibody also partially blocks mouse AM  binding of particles, indicating that low levels of ED31  (MARCO) are present and functional on these cells. In these  studies, we used normal, healthy looking mice housed in  conventional facilities, not a &#x0201c;clean room&#x0201d; barrier facility.  Expression of MARCO is induced on lung and liver macrophages in mice infected with <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). It  is possible that our mice expressed MARCO because of  low-level activation from their less clean environmental  surroundings, a possibility yet to be formally tested. It is  also noteworthy that both PI and anti-MARCO (ED31)  cause lower levels of inhibition of unopsonized particle  binding by mouse AMs compared with that seen with  hamster AMs. Whether this reflects a significant difference  (e.g., the presence of other receptor[s]), minor species, or  technical variables remains to be determined.</p><p>Our finding that MARCO mediates AM binding of particles defines a novel and immunologically important function for MARCO. As MARCO mediates binding of both  inert particles and potentially pathogenic microorganisms,  it will be interesting to determine how binding by MARCO  modulates AM bactericidal functions. Specifically, the laudable absence of AM activation that accompanies binding  (and ingestion) of inert environmental dusts may prove  harmful for encounters with viable pathogens. Additional  studies of the function of MARCO may provide more insight into the role of AMs in the initial, innate response of  the lung to inhaled particles and pathogens.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>SR-A&#x02013;deficient and &#x02013;sufficient AMs bind TiO<sub>2 </sub>equally. (A)  Representative photomicrograph showing approximately similar binding of  particles by SR-A&#x02013;deficient (SR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>) and wild-type (SR<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup>) AMs incubated with unopsonized TiO<sub>2</sub> (original magnification 400). (B) SR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and  SR<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup> AMs were pretreated with the SR blocker PI or the control polyanion CS or left untreated, and their binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> was determined by flow  cytometry. (C) SR<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and SR<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup> AMs show similar binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> in  vivo as determined by intratracheal instillation of TiO<sub>2</sub> followed by BAL  and flow cytometric analysis. TiO<sub>2</sub> binding is expressed as increase in flow  cytometric RAS. The data represent the mean (&#x000b1; SEM) of three separate  experiments (B) and three mice per treated group compared with one control (C). *Significantly different from TiO<sub>2</sub> alone, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.006.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The mAb PAL-1 blocks AM binding of TiO<sub>2</sub>. Hamster AMs  were untreated or pretreated with PI, CS, mAb PAL-1, and an isotype-matched control mAb (IgM), and their binding of TiO<sub>2</sub> was determined  by flow cytometry as described in Materials and Methods. TiO<sub>2</sub> binding is  expressed as increase in flow cytometric RAS. The data represent mean  (&#x000b1; SEM) of 10 separate experiments. *Significantly different from TiO<sub>2</sub>  alone, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="TI"><label>Table I</label><caption><p>mAb PAL-1 Inhibits AM Binding of a Panel of  Unopsonized Particles </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Particle</th><th/><th>Percent inhibition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">TiO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 10)</td><td/><td>67 &#x000b1; 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 2)</td><td/><td>78 &#x000b1; 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sulfated latex beads (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 2)</td><td/><td>85 &#x000b1; 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SiO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">52 &#x000b1; 24</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Hamster AMs were left untreated or pretreated with mAb PAL-1 or an  isotype-matched control mAb and their binding of particles determined as  described in Materials and Methods. Particle binding is expressed as percent  inhibition of TiO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 10), Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 2), latex bead (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 2), and SiO<sub>2</sub>  (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3) binding by mAb PAL-1. No significant inhibition of particle binding was observed with a control IgM (range is from &#x02212;18 to 7% inhibition).  &#x000a0;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Immunoprecipitation of  the AM surface protein recognized by  mAb PAL-1. Hamster AMs were surface-labeled with sulfo-NHS-biotin,  extracted with Triton X-100, precleared with anti&#x02013;mouse IgM magnetic beads, and immunoprecipitated  with mAb PAL-1 or a control IgM  bound to anti&#x02013;mouse magnetic beads.  Immunoprecipitates were analyzed  using reducing (R) or nonreducing  (NR) SDS-PAGE as described in  Materials and Methods. Relative molecular mass is indicated (kD).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical detection of the molecule recognized by  PAL-1. (A) Photomicrographs of cytospins of hamster BAL cells. Frozen sections  of lung, liver, and lymph nodes were stained with mAb PAL-1 or an irrelevant  control mAb. Original magnification: 400 for BAL cells, 200 for tissue sections.  (B) The expression of the molecule recognized by mAb PAL-1 was analyzed by  flow cytometry. Single-cell suspensions prepared from the indicated organs  (CLN, cervical lymph node; MLN, mesenteric lymph node; PP, Peyer's patch;  PMN, neutrophils) or hamster BAL (AM) were incubated with either mAb  PAL-1 or an isotype-matched control mAb followed by goat anti&#x02013;mouse IgM&#x02013; FITC and analyzed by flow cytometry. The data are presented as relative fluorescence intensity (mean channel number from flow cytometric analysis). White  bar, control; hatched bar, IgM; black bar, PAL-1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f4a"/><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f4b"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>(A and B) Transfection of COS cells with a cDNA clone (isolated by an expression cloning strategy) confers PAL-1 reactivity. COS cells were transfected with the  isolated cDNA clone (A) or the empty vector (B); cytospins prepared 48 h later, and they  were immunostained with mAb PAL-1. Control IgM antibody showed no labeling (not  shown). (C) Transfection of COS cells with MARCO cDNA (for sequence identification,  see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) confers mAb PAL-1 inhibitable TiO<sub>2</sub> binding. COS cells, transfected with  MARCO cDNA, were pretreated with mAb PAL-1 and a control mAb and their binding  of TiO<sub>2</sub> determined using a flow cytometric assay. The data represent mean (&#x000b1; SEM) RAS  increase of five separate experiments. *Significantly different from TiO<sub>2</sub> alone, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f5ab"/><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f5c"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>(A) Nucleotide and deduced protein sequences of hamster MARCO. Conserved cysteine residues in the SRCRs are boxed. Putative carbohydrate attachment sites are circled. The consensus polyadenylation signal is underlined. The start ATG is indicated with an arrow. A kink in the collagenous domain is indicated by dotted underline. (B) Comparison of hamster, mouse, and human MARCO. Amino acids were aligned using the Align program (GeneWorks package; Intelligenetics). Regions of identity are boxed. These sequence data are available from GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ under  accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF125191">AF125191</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f6a"/><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f6b"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="TII"><label>Table II</label><caption><p>Amino Acid Identity between Hamster, Mouse, and  Human MARCO </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Hamster MARCO domains</th><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="3">Percent amino acid identity</th></tr><tr><th>Human MARCO</th><th/><th>Mouse MARCO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Cytoplasmic</td><td/><td>48</td><td/><td>77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Transmembrane</td><td/><td>61</td><td/><td>78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spacer</td><td/><td>58</td><td/><td>65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Collagenous</td><td/><td>76</td><td/><td>77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SRCR</td><td/><td>65</td><td/><td>77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Across all domains</td><td/><td>65</td><td/><td>77</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Amino acid identity was determined by comparing the indicated putative domains with each other using the Align program in the Biology  Workbench (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biology.ncsa.uiuc.edu">http://biology.ncsa.uiuc.edu</ext-link>).    &#x000a0;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Effect of mAb PAL-1 on bacteria and yeast binding by AMs.  Hamster AMs were left untreated or pretreated with PI, CS, mAb PAL-1, and  a control mAb (IgM). Following pretreatment, AM binding of <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>S. aureus,</italic> and the yeast particle <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (Zymosan) was determined by  flow cytometry. The data represent mean (&#x000b1; SEM) green fluorescence of four  separate experiments. *Significantly different from particle alone, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f7"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>(A&#x02013;D) Human AMs express MARCO. Immunostaining of normal volunteer BAL cytocentrifuge preparations (A) and surgical lung tissue  specimens (C) showed strong labeling by a rabbit anti&#x02013;human MARCO antibody; control rabbit IgG showed only minimal nonspecific background  staining (B, D) (original magnification 400). (E) Lysates prepared from BAL cells collected from adult volunteers (2/5 similar results shown) were analyzed by reducing SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted with a rabbit anti&#x02013;human MARCO antibody or control rabbit IgG (Ctrl). Relative molecular mass  standards are indicated (kD).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f8ad"/><graphic xlink:href="JEM990275.f8e"/></fig></sec><ack><p>We thank Dr. Scott Shepard and Marshall Katler for assistance in sequencing and Dr. G. Kraal for providing  anti&#x02013;mouse MARCO antibodies.</p><p>This work was supported by grants NIEHS 00002 and ES08129.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations used in this paper</title><def-list><def-item><term>AM</term><def><p>alveolar macrophage</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BAL</term><def><p>bronchoalveolar lavage</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BSS</term><def><p>balanced salt solution</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CS</term><def><p>chondroitin sulfate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI</term><def><p>polyinosinic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RAS</term><def><p>right angle scatter</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SR</term><def><p>scavenger receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SRCR</term><def><p>scavenger receptor cysteine-rich domain</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other">Brain, J.D. 1985. Macrophages in the respiratory tract. <italic>In</italic>  Handbook of Physiology. I.A.P. Fishman, editor. American  Physiological Society, Bethesda, MD. 447&#x02013;471.</citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macrophages, dusts and pulmonary diseases</article-title><source>Exp Lung Res</source><year>1987</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3552644</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phagocytosis by zippers and triggers</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14732161</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phagocytosis</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><year>1994</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7748161</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parod</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brain</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uptake of latex particles by macrophages: characterization using flow cytometry</article-title><source>Am J  Physiol</source><year>1983</year><volume>245</volume><fpage>C220</fpage><lpage>C225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6614156</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parod</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brain</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune opsonin-independent phagocytosis by pulmonary macrophages</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1986</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>2041</fpage><lpage>2049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3081636</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobzik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Godleski</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brain</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective down-regulation of alveolar macrophage oxidative response to opsonin-independent phagocytosis</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1990</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>4312</fpage><lpage>4319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2160498</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Haskill</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential production of tumor necrosis factor, macrophage colony stimulating factor, and interleukin 1 by human alveolar macrophages</article-title><source>J Leukoc Biol</source><year>1989</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2649630</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillemin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rom</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced IL-1&#x003b2; and tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1; release and messenger RNA expression in macrophages from idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis or after asbestos exposure</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1993</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>4188</fpage><lpage>4196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8473757</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobzik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lung macrophage uptake of unopsonized environmental particulates. Role of scavenger-type receptors</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1995</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7541421</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular flypaper and atherosclerosis: structure of the macrophage scavenger receptor</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>1992</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1585457</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hampton</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Golenbock</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Penman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raetz</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition and plasma clearance of endotoxin by scavenger receptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1991</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1852209</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Herz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structures and functions of multiligand lipoprotein receptors: macrophage scavenger receptor and LDL receptor-related protein (LRP)</article-title><source>Annu Rev  Biochem</source><year>1994</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7979249</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabrecky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsudaira</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Type I macrophage scavenger receptor contains alpha-helical and collagen-like coiled coils</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2300204</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Penman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coiled-coil fibrous domains mediate ligand binding by macrophage scavenger receptor type II</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2300208</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scavenger receptors in innate immunity</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8729442</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamakubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scavenger receptor family proteins: roles for atherosclerosis, host defence and disorders of the central nervous system</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9711230</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elomaa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pikkarainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuuyyila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raatikainen-Asokas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sariola</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the human macrophage MARCO receptor and characterization of its bacteria-binding region</article-title><source>J  Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>4530</fpage><lpage>4538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9468508</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elomaa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kangas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahlberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuukanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sormunen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liakka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thesleff</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning of a novel bacteria binding receptor structurally related to scavenger receptors and expressed in a subset of macrophages</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7867067</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Laan</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dopp</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haworth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pikkarainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kangas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elomaa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Dijkstra</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation and functional involvement of macrophage scavenger receptor MARCO in clearance of bacteria in vivo</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9916718</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Laan</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kangas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dopp</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Broug-Holub</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Elomaa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macrophage scavenger receptor MARCO: in vitro and in vivo regulation and involvement in the anti-bacterial host defense</article-title><source>Immunol  Lett</source><year>1997</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9232452</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frevert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Imrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sioutas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobzik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alveolar macrophage interaction with air pollution particulates</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>1997</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1191</fpage><lpage>1195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9400722</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brain</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohannon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An in vivo hamster bioassay to assess the toxicity of particulates for the lung</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><year>1982</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6925426</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jishaga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A role for macrophage scavenger receptors in atherosclerosis and susceptibility to infection</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>386</volume><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9069289</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Imrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobzik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lung macrophage uptake of environmental particulates: a flow cytometric assay</article-title><source>Cytometry</source><year>1995</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7600897</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="other">Kobzik, L., and H.W. Schmidt. 1996. Immunohistochemistry of nitric oxide synthase and nitric oxide-related products.  <italic>In</italic> Methods in Nitric Oxide Research. M. Feelisch and J.S.  Stamler, editors. John Wiley and Sons Ltd., New York. 229&#x02013; 236.</citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="other">Coligan, J.E., A.M. Kruisbeek, D.H. Margulies, E.M. Shevach, and E.M. Strober, editors. 1994. Use of monoclonal  antibodies for expression cloning. Current Protocols in Immunology. Vol. 2. John Wiley and Sons, Inc., New York.  10.18.1&#x02013;10.18.6.</citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dockery</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>CA</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Acute respiratory effects of particulate air pollution</article-title><source>Annu Rev Public Health</source><year>1994</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8054077</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dockery</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased mortality in Philadelphia associated with daily air pollution concentrations</article-title><source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source><year>1992</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1546841</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and daily mortality: a review and meta analysis</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8287841</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Sizto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships between air pollution levels and hospital admissions in Southern Ontario</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>1983</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6850488</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complement receptors and phagocytosis</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>1992</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1675856</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmskov</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensenius</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collectins: collagenous C-type lectins of the innate immune defense system</article-title><source>Immunol Today</source><year>1994</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8155265</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sastry</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezekowitz</surname><given-names>RAB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collectins: pattern recognition molecules involved in first line host defense</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>1993</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8452675</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ofek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldhar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keisari</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonopsonic phagocytosis of microorganisms</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8561460</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dransfield</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of apoptotic cells by phagocytes</article-title><source>Experientia</source><year>1996</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>950</fpage><lpage>956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8917725</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palecanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobzik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opsonin-independent phagocytosis: role of scavenger type receptors</article-title><source>Curr Trends  Immunol</source><year>1998</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>147</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Imrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobzik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lung epithelial cell (A549) interaction with unopsonized environmental particulates: quantitation of particle-specific binding and IL-8 production</article-title><source>Exp Lung Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8886755</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashkenas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ancient, highly conserved family of cysteine-rich protein domains revealed by cloning type I and type II macrophage scavenger receptors</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1990</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>8810</fpage><lpage>8814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1978939</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn><p>This study complies with National Institutes of Health guidelines and was approved by the Institutional Review Committees on Animals of the Harvard School of Public Health.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>


