<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9314552</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2199061</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Critical Role for Syk in Signal Transduction and Phagocytosis Mediated by Fc&#x003b3; Receptors on Macrophages </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>Mary T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>Patrick S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzer-Attas</surname><given-names>Cheryl J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Fanying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lowell</surname><given-names>Clifford</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tybulewicz</surname><given-names>Victor L. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>DeFranco</surname><given-names>Anthony L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1c0b450N0x3f96dc8">From the G.W. Hooper Foundation, <label>&#x0002a;</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, and  <label>&#x02021;</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California, San Francisco, California 94143-0552; and the <label>&#x000a7;</label>National Institute for Medical Research, London NW7 1AA, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Dr. Mary T. Crowley, Scripps Clinic and Research Foundation, 10550 N. Torrey Pines Rd., IMM 25, La Jolla, CA 92037. Phone: 619-784-2195; FAX: 619-784-9180; E-mail:  <email>mtcrow&#x00040;scripps.edu</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>6</day><month>10</month><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>186</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>1997</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>1997</year></date></history><copyright-year>1997</copyright-year><abstract><p>Receptors on macrophages for the Fc region of IgG (Fc&#x003b3;R) mediate a number of responses  important for host immunity. Signaling events necessary for these responses are likely initiated by the activation of Src-family and Syk-family tyrosine kinases after Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking.  Macrophages derived from Syk-deficient (Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) mice were defective in phagocytosis of particles bound by Fc&#x003b3;Rs, as well as in many Fc&#x003b3;R-induced signaling events, including tyrosine  phosphorylation of a number of cellular substrates and activation of MAP kinases. In contrast,  Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages exhibited normal responses to another potent macrophage stimulus, lipopolysaccharide. Phagocytosis of latex beads and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> bacteria was also not affected.  Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages exhibited formation of polymerized actin structures opposing particles  bound to the cells by Fc&#x003b3;Rs (actin cups), but failed to proceed to internalization. Interestingly,  inhibitors of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase also blocked Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis at this  stage. Thus, PI 3-kinase may participate in a Syk-dependent signaling pathway critical for  Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis. Macrophages derived from mice deficient for the three members  of the Src-family of kinases expressed in these cells, Hck, Fgr, and Lyn, exhibited poor Syk activation upon Fc&#x003b3;R engagement, accompanied by a delay in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis.  These observations demonstrate that Syk is critical for Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis, as well as  for signal transduction in macrophages. Additionally, our findings provide evidence to support  a model of sequential tyrosine kinase activation by Fc&#x003b3;R's analogous to models of signaling by  the B and T cell antigen receptors.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Cross-linking of receptors for Fc regions of IgG  (Fc&#x003b3;Rs)<sup>1</sup> triggers cellular events that are crucial for a  variety of immune responses. These include phagocytosis,  production of cytokines and chemokines, release of agents  that damage microorganisms or infected cells, and changes  in expression of cell surface proteins involved in cell&#x02013;cell  adhesion and antigen presentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). The important  roles for these receptors in antibody-mediated allergic and  inflammatory responses have been demonstrated in mice  made deficient for Fc&#x003b3;Rs by targeted gene disruption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Thus, the Fc&#x003b3;Rs allow the humoral and cellular aspects  of immunity to communicate and cooperate in expanding,  sustaining, and regulating immune responses.</p><p>Signaling events triggered by Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking are believed to be largely analogous to the events induced by engagement of B cell and T cell antigen receptors. Tyrosine  kinases of the Src and Syk families become activated and  associate with specific recognition sequences known as immunoreceptor tyrosine-based activation motifs (ITAMs),  contained within the intracellular domains of some of the  Fc&#x003b3;R subunits. Targets of these activated tyrosine kinases  include the Fc&#x003b3;R itself, enzymes that generate second messengers (e.g., phospholipase C-&#x003b3;1 and phosphatidylinositol  3-kinase [PI 3-kinase]), and regulators of Ras and other  Ras-like G proteins (e.g., Shc, Vav) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>).</p><p>An important function of Fc&#x003b3;Rs on macrophages and  monocytes is their ability to promote phagocytosis. Ingestion  of IgG-coated cells serves to remove and destroy invading  microorganisms or infected cells. In addition, phagocytosis  provides a means for internalizing antigen for processing  and presentation to T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). The molecular mechanisms  by which Fc&#x003b3;Rs trigger the phagocytic process are poorly  understood. A role for Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated protein tyrosine  phosphorylation in inducing phagocytosis is suggested by  the finding that protein tyrosine kinase inhibitors block  phagocytosis of IgG-coated particles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Moreover, the  intracellular tyrosine kinase Syk associates with Fc&#x003b3;RII (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>)  and with the tyrosine phosphorylated &#x003b3; chain of Fc&#x003b3;RI  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) and Fc&#x003b3;RIII (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>), and has been implicated in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis. For example, COS-1 cells transfected with human Fc&#x003b3;Rs exhibit enhanced phagocytosis  upon cotransfection of human Syk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Similarly, cells expressing Fc&#x003b3;RIII-Syk (CD16-Syk) chimeras can phagocytose particles that cross-link the CD16 portion of the molecule (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>); chimeras containing kinase-inactive Syk do not  mediate internalization. How Syk promotes Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis is unclear, but inositol phospholipid metabolism is likely to be an important downstream signaling  event since wortmannin, a potent inhibitor of PI 3-kinase,  prevents Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). To test directly  the importance of Syk for Fc&#x003b3;R-induced signaling and  phagocytosis, we have examined these events in cultured  macrophages derived from mice genetically deficient for  Syk. The role of Syk in signal transduction in response to  Fc&#x003b3;R engagement and stimulation with the bacterial endotoxin LPS were also examined. The results reported here  demonstrate that Syk is required for Fc&#x003b3;R-induced phagocytosis, but not for phagocytosis of latex beads or microorganisms. In addition, Syk was found to play an important  role for many Fc&#x003b3;R-induced signaling events, but not for  various LPS-induced signaling events or biological responses.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec disp-level="3"><title>Antibodies.</title><p>The hybridomas producing the 2.4G2 monoclonal rat antibody, the MAR18.5 mouse anti&#x02013;rat Ig &#x003ba; chain  monoclonal antibody, and the anti&#x02013;sheep red blood cell monoclonal antibodies TIB 111, TIB 114, and TIB 109, were obtained  from the American Type Culture Collection (Rockville, MD).  Monoclonal antiphosphotyrosine-agarose was purchased from  <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content> (St. Louis, MO). The 4G10 antiphosphotyrosine antibody was prepared and used as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Horseradish peroxidase&#x02013;conjugated sheep anti&#x02013;mouse IgG antibody  was obtained from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham Corp.</named-content> (Arlington Heights, IL).  Horseradish peroxidase&#x02013;conjugated sheep anti&#x02013;rabbit IgG antibody was obtained from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="boehringer">Boehringer Mannheim Biochemicals</named-content>  (Indianapolis, IL). Protein G&#x02013;Sepharose was obtained from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pharmacia">Pharmacia LKB Biotechnology Inc.</named-content> (Piscataway, NJ). Anti&#x02013;human  Vav protein antibody was obtained from Upstate Biotechnology  Inc. (Lake Placid, NY). Antibodies to p38, Erk1/2, and Jun  NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal (JNK) kinases were obtained from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sbct">Santa Cruz Biotechnology</named-content> (Santa Cruz, CA). The rabbit anti-Syk antibody has  been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). Anti-Shc antisera was generated by immunizing with a glutathione S-transferase (GST) fusion protein containing amino acids 359&#x02013;473 of the human Shc protein. Specific antibodies were obtained by affinity column purification of antibodies  reactive with the Shc-GST fusion protein, but not with GST  alone.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Reagents.</title><p>Wortmannin was obtained from Calbiochem Corp.  (San Diego, CA). Fluorescent phalloidins were from Molecular  Probes Inc. (Eugene, OR). Myelin Basic Protein was from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma  Chemical Co.</named-content> The recombinant GST fused to the COOH-terminal of Jun (GST&#x02013;c-Jun) fusion protein was purified from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> lysate as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Purified LPS from <italic>Salmonella  minnesota</italic> was obtained from List Biological Laboratories (Campbell, CA).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Cells.</title><p>Mice heterozygous for a disruption of the <italic>syk</italic> gene  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>) were bred, and the resulting embryos were dissected at day  17 of gestation to obtain the fetal liver. Genotyping of offspring  was performed by Southern blotting as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>).  Single-cell suspensions were resuspended at 10<sup>6</sup> cells per ml in  RPMI-1640 media supplemented with 10% FCS, 2 mM sodium  pyruvate, 1 mM glutamine, and 50 &#x003bc;M 2-mercaptoethanol, nonessential amino acids, and 10% L cell conditioned media (LCM)  as a source of M-CSF and GM-CSF. The adherent monolayer  cultures generated by this protocol contained primarily cells of  the macrophage lineage as determined by adherent morphology,  expression of CD11b, CD16, and CD32, but not Gr-1, or B or T  lymphocyte markers.</p><p>Generation of the <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic>/<italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic>/<italic>lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> strain of mice is described  elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Macrophages from normal and <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic>/<italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic>/<italic>lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic>  mice were isolated from bone marrow. Marrow from tibia and  femur bones was eluted in DMEM. Clumps were removed by  rigorous pipetting and passage through 70-&#x003bc;m nylon mesh.  Erythrocytes were lysed by adding 2 vol of 1.44% NH<sub>4</sub>Cl. The  cells in these suspensions were recovered by centrifugation. Cells  were cultured in media described for fetal liver cultures. Nonadherent cells were removed 1&#x02013;2 d later and transferred to a fresh  150-mm plate. Nonadherent cells were removed from this secondary culture 4 d later and discarded. The adherent cultures  were used 5&#x02013;7 d after initial harvest from the mice, when confluency was achieved. Cultures generated via this protocol were almost purely macrophages, as indicated by the criteria listed above,  and contained very few, if any, fibroblasts.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Binding and Phagocytosis of Antibody-coated Erythrocytes (EA).</title><p>EA were prepared in calcium- and magnesium-free PBS by incubating sheep erythrocytes (Accurate Chemical and Scientific Corporation, Westbury, NY) (10<sup>9</sup>/ml) with a subagglutinating concentration of rabbit anti&#x02013;sheep red blood cell antibodies (Nordic  Immunology, Tilburg, Netherlands). Cultured macrophages were  grown on 12-mm glass coverslips and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C with EA  (10<sup>7</sup>/ml) for 30 min. Unbound EA was washed away, and some  coverslips were fixed in 2% glutaraldehyde in PBS for 30 min,  and were mounted for phase microscopy of rosettes as described  below. To observe internalization, some coverslips were incubated in hypotonic buffer (1.4% NH<sub>4</sub>Cl) at room temperature for  5 min to lyse uninternalized EA before fixation. For studies on  the rate of phagocytosis, EA particles were first bound to macrophages on ice for 30 min, followed by a 5-min centrifugation at  150 <italic>g.</italic> Phagocytosis was initiated by addition of warm medium,  and cultures were placed in a 37&#x000b0;C incubator. Uninternalized EA  were lysed by addition of H<sub>2</sub>O for 30 s, and cells were fixed as  above.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Fluorescence Microscopy.</title><p>To visualize actin cups, cells on coverslips were incubated in the presence or absence of cytochalasin  D (1 &#x003bc;M) for 15 min. Cells were incubated 2&#x02013;4 min with EA,  and were then fixed in 3.7% formaldehyde for 10 min. Alternatively, to achieve a high number of stable actin cups, cells were incubated on ice with EA (10<sup>7</sup>/ml) for 30 min. Unbound EA were  washed away, and slips were processed for fluorescence microscopy. Cells on 12-mm glass coverslips were fixed in 3.7% formaldehyde for 10 min, and were then permeabilized in .01% Triton  X-100 in PBS for 5 min. Cells were then stained with BODIPY-phalloidin or Oregon green-phalloidin (5 U/ml in PBS) for 15  min. Cells were observed by phase contrast and fluorescence microscopy (Axiophot microscope; Carl Zeiss, Inc., Thornwood, NY).  To visualize LPS-induced actin-rich structures, cells on coverslips  were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C with or without LPS (100 ng/ml) for 1 h.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Cell Stimulation.</title><p>Before stimulation for signaling experiments, cells were starved for 2 h in culture media lacking LCM.  For Fc&#x003b3;R stimulation, adherent cultures were incubated on ice  for 30 min with 2.4G2 hybridoma supernatant. Cells were then  warmed to 37&#x000b0;C and treated with cross-linking antibody (10 &#x003bc;g/ ml MAR18.5) for indicated times. Unstimulated cultures were  incubated on ice, and at 37&#x000b0;C in culture media without LCM.  For LPS activation, cells were starved as above. LPS (1 &#x003bc;g/ml)  was then added directly to culture vessels for the indicated times.  Plates of Fc&#x003b3;R- and LPS-stimulated cells were washed with cold  PBS containing 1 mM sodium vanadate. Ice-cold lysis buffer  consisting of 1% Triton-X-100, 50 mM Hepes buffer, pH 7.4,  150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EGTA,  100 mM NaF, 1 mM PMSF, and 1 mM NaVO<sub>4</sub> was added directly to the flasks. Cultures were lysed on ice for 10 min.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Immunoprecipitations and Immunoblotting.</title><p>Anti-Shc immunoprecipitations were carried out as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). For antiphosphotyrosine immunoprecipitations, samples were adjusted  to RIPA (150 mM NaCl, 1.0% NP-40, 0.5% deoxycholate, 0.1%  SDS, and 50 mM Tris buffer, pH 8.0). Immunoprecipitations  were carried out for 8&#x02013;10 h at 4&#x000b0;C. SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting were carried out as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), with the  exception that to detect the electrophoretic mobility shift of p42  Erk2, soluble lysate proteins were separated on 12.5% SDS-PAGE containing an acrylamide/bis-acrylamide ratio of 120:1,  and were transferred to nitrocellulose.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Immunoprecipitation and In Vitro Protein Kinase Assays.</title><p>Cell lysates prepared as described above were precleared with 25 &#x003bc;l of  protein A&#x02013;Sepharose, and were then incubated with 10 &#x003bc;l of  anti-Syk, anti-JNK, or anti-Erk2 antibody for 1 h on ice. Immune  complexes were collected on 25 &#x003bc;l Protein A&#x02013;Sepharose, and  were washed twice with lysis buffer and twice with kinase assay  buffer (25 mM Hepes, pH 7.6, 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 20 mM &#x003b2;-glycerol  phosphate, 1 mM DTT, or 20 mM MOPS, pH 7.6, 20 mM  MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 30 mM &#x003b2;-glycerol phosphate, 5 mM EGTA, and 1 mM  DTT for JNK or Erk kinase assays, respectively). Reactions were  performed at 30&#x000b0;C for 15 min in the presence of 10 &#x003bc;Ci of  &#x003b3;-[<sup>33</sup>P]ATP using 20&#x02013;25 &#x003bc;g GST&#x02013;c-Jun or Myelin Basic Protein  as substrate for JNK or Erk2, respectively. Anti-Syk immunoprecipitates were washed twice with lysis buffer and twice with kinase assay buffer (20 mM Tris HCl, pH 8.0, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1%  NP-40). The beads were incubated in 50 &#x003bc;l of kinase assay buffer  plus 10 &#x003bc;Ci of &#x003b3;-[<sup>33</sup>P]ATP for 10 min at room temperature.  Erk1/2, JNK, and Syk kinase reactions were stopped by adding  SDS-PAGE sample buffer, separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose, and were analyzed using a PhosphorImager (Molecular Dynamics, Sunnyvale, CA).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Cytokine ELISA Assays.</title><p>Macrophages were incubated in culture media containing LCM, in 24-well plates at a density of 5 &#x000d7;  10<sup>4</sup>/well in 1.5 ml of media. Cultures received LPS at the indicated doses, and supernatants were collected from cultures at the  indicated times after initial exposure. Duplicate supernatants were  collected from two separate wells at each time point. Supernatants  were stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0; until assay. Cytokine concentrations in the  supernatants were measured using murine cytokine ELISA detection kits from Biosource International (Camarillo, CA).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec disp-level="4"><title>Defective Fc&#x003b3;R-Mediated Phagocytosis in SYK<sup>&#x02212;</sup> Macrophages.</title><p>The engulfment of cells and particulate matter is  an important function of the tissue macrophage. Among  the receptors known to promote phagocytosis are the  Fc&#x003b3;Rs and the complement receptor. To examine the relative importance of Syk and members of the Src-family of  tyrosine kinases for Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis, we established primary cultures of fetal liver&#x02013;derived wild-type and  Syk-deficient macrophages, or of bone marrow&#x02013;derived  wild-type and Src-family kinase-deficient (Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/ Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) macrophages in CSF-1&#x02013;containing medium. None  of the other known Src-family tyrosine kinases were detected in the latter macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>).</p><p>The capacity of these cultured fetal liver&#x02013;derived or bone  marrow&#x02013;derived macrophages to mediate particle uptake  via their Fc&#x003b3;Rs was tested (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Macrophages were incubated with IgG-coated sheep erythrocytes (EA) either on  ice or at 37&#x000b0;C. Wild-type, Syk-deficient, and Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/ Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells bound EA equally well under either condition.  At 37&#x000b0;C, wild-type and Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells internalized  the bound EA particles, although the Src family&#x02013;deficient  macrophages internalized the bound particles more slowly.  To examine this difference more readily, the macrophages  were allowed to bind the EA particles at 0&#x000b0;C, and were  then warmed to 37&#x000b0;C to permit internalization to proceed.  Under these conditions, wild-type macrophages internalized the EA particles rapidly, with a substantial percentage  internalized by 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C, and near maximal internalization by 10 min. In contrast, the Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages had internalized very few particles by 5 min, but  had internalized a substantial percentage by 10 min. At this  time, there was less internalization than that seen with wild-type macrophages, but after 30 min the difference was minimal (data not shown). In contrast, Syk-deficient macrophages began engulfment, but were unable to complete  phagocytosis of the bound EA particles. This effect was  readily apparent when the macrophages were subjected to  hypotonic conditions that lysed the erythrocytes attached to  the surface of the macrophage, but not the fully engulfed EA  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, <italic>b</italic> and <italic>c</italic>). Additionally, wild-type macrophages bound  and internalized erythrocytes coated with IgG3, IgG2a, or  IgG2b antibodies, whereas Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages bound but  failed to internalize these particles (data not shown). Antibody-coated erythrocytes remained bound to Fc&#x003b3;Rs on  the surface of Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages for several days in culture,  indicating that the inhibition of phagocytosis was complete,  and was not simply delayed. The phagocytosis observed in  these experiments was Fc&#x003b3;R dependent as uncoated erythrocytes were not phagocytosed or bound by normal or  Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages. These findings demonstrate an absolute  requirement for the presence of Syk to accomplish Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis in macrophages. </p><p>The difference in phagocytic ability of Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages  compared to Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages was unexpected, as both of these types of kinases are thought to play  an important role in signaling by the family of receptors  that includes Fc&#x003b3;Rs and the antigen receptors of B and T  cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Studies in a variety of systems have suggested  that Src-family tyrosine kinases are responsible for initiating  signaling of these immunoreceptors by phosphorylating the  two tyrosines of the receptor ITAM, and thereby providing  a mechanism for recruiting and activating the tyrosine kinase Syk (or ZAP-70 in T cells) to the engaged receptor  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Indeed, as predicted by this general model, we  found that Syk was only poorly activated after Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking in Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages as compared to  its activation in normal cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). It should be noted,  however, that there was a small amount of Fc&#x003b3;R-induced  activation of Syk in the Src family mutant cells, indicating  that Syk could participate in Fc&#x003b3;R signaling to some extent, even in the absence of these three Src-family tyrosine  kinases. </p><p>The defect in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis of Syk-deficient macrophages did not represent a general defect in the  phagocytic ability of these cells. There were no discernible  differences in the abilities of wild-type, Syk-deficient, or  Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages to phagocytose latex beads  ranging in size from 0.2 to 5.5 &#x003bc;m, or to engulf and destroy yeast and <italic>E. coli</italic> (data not shown). Furthermore, after  pretreatment with LPS, all three macrophage populations  exhibited increased phagocytic capacity for bacteria (data  not shown). The attachment and engulfment of microorganisms most likely represents binding of complex carbohydrates on the surface of the microbe to lectin-like glycoproteins or integrins expressed by the macrophage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>).  Evidently these receptors do not require Syk for triggering  phagocytosis.</p><p>To characterize further the defect in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated  phagocytosis of Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages, we next examined the  position of actin structures after EA binding. Actin is likely  to play an important role in phagocytosis since it is concentrated in the macrophage cytoplasm surrounding the particle being engulfed, and since cytochalasin D treatment,  which blocks actin polymerization, abrogates phagocytosis  without affecting particle binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). We used fluorescent phalloidin to visualize the polymerized actin cytoskeleton in Syk-deficient and wild-type cells. Phagocytic,  actin-lined cups formed around antibody-coated erythrocytes bound by Syk-deficient cells, and were indistinguishable from those formed by wild-type cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <italic>a&#x02013;d</italic>) or  by Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells (data not shown). Actin cup formation occurred at 4&#x000b0;C or at 37&#x000b0;C, and was blocked by cytochalasin D treatment. Syk-deficient cells were presumably unable to effect the closure of the pocket generated by  the advancing membrane edges that created the phagocytic  cup. How macrophages and other professional phagocytes  achieve this final stage of phagocytosis is unknown. At  37&#x000b0;C, but not at 4&#x000b0;C, the actin cup structures were dynamic, and their dissolution occurred at about the same  time as internalization was completed in wild-type macrophages. Interestingly, Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells also exhibited dissolution of the actin cups around the bound EA, although these  particles were never internalized or released. </p><p>We next examined whether Syk participates in other  macrophage-signaling pathways involving cytoskeletal rearrangements. Macrophages responding to LPS develop distinct morphological changes, including the development of  actin-rich ruffles. As LPS stimulation of macrophages leads  to tyrosine phosphorylation of Syk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), we asked whether  Syk participated in LPS-induced cytoskeletal changes. When  exposed to LPS, Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells developed actin-rich ruffles indistinguishable from those induced on normal cells (data  not shown). Thus, LPS does not require Syk to effect these  changes in the actin-based cytoskeleton.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Impaired Signaling Via Fc&#x003b3;R In Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> Macrophages.</title><p>To examine the mechanism behind the observed phagocytic defect of Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages, we looked for defects in tyrosine  phosphorylation of cellular proteins and defects in signal  transduction pathways known to be dependent upon receptor-activated tyrosine kinases. After cross-linking of Fc&#x003b3;RII and Fc&#x003b3;RIII on the surface of Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and wild-type  macrophages with the antibody 2.4G2, total cellular proteins were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and antiphosphotyrosine immunoblotting. We observed a number of proteins  that were inducibly tyrosine phosphorylated in normal  cells. The most obvious of these had apparent molecular  weights of 180, 150, 145, 120, 100, 85, 70, 60, 56, 52, 48,  and 42 kD, and are indicated by arrows in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> <italic>a.</italic> Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup>  macrophages were defective in most aspects of this response. Some of the induced tyrosine phosphoproteins, for  example, the 42-kD band corresponding to Erk2 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> <italic>c</italic>),  were conspicuously absent upon Fc&#x003b3;R stimulation in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup>  cells, and many other proteins became only weakly phosphorylated after receptor cross-linking. In contrast, a few  proteins, including two at 56 and 52 kD which may correspond to members of the Src family of tyrosine kinases, did  exhibit induced tyrosine phosphorylation comparable to  that seen in wild-type cells. </p><p>We then examined the induced tyrosine phosphorylation  of the important signaling components Shc and p145<sup>Ship</sup> (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> <italic>b</italic>). Within 5 min of Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking in normal cells,  we observed increased tyrosine phosphorylation of Shc  and p145<sup>Ship</sup> as well as the induced association of Shc with  p145<sup>Ship</sup>, in agreement with previous results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). In contrast, in Syk-deficient cells, Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking induced only  weak tyrosine phosphorylation of Shc and p145<sup>Ship</sup>. These  results show that Syk plays a principal role in the rapid tyrosine phosphorylation of many cellular substrates after  Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Requirement for Syk in Fc&#x003b3;R-induced Activation of MAP Kinases.</title><p>The lack of Fc&#x003b3;R-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of p42<sup>MAPK</sup> (Erk2) in the Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>)  was quite striking. MAP kinases become activated upon dual  phosphorylation of threonine and tyrosine residues in a TxY  motif. In the case of Erk1 and Erk2, this dual phosphorylation results in a mobility shift upon SDS-PAGE. Therefore,  we examined the effect of Fc&#x003b3;R stimulation on Erk1 and  Erk2 electrophoretic mobility. As expected, p42<sup>MAPK</sup> (Erk2)  and p44<sup>MAPK</sup> (Erk1) exhibited a clear shift in mobility in  normal macrophages stimulated through the Fc&#x003b3;Rs. This  response was absent in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> <italic>a</italic> and data  not shown). Moreover, in vitro kinase assays revealed that  Fc&#x003b3;R stimulation led to a large increase in Erk2 MAP kinase activity in wild-type macrophages, but to a small or no  increase in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> <italic>b</italic>). </p><p>These results do not reflect a generalized defect in  MAPK activition in the Syk-deficient macrophages, since  the ability of LPS to induce a mobility shift of p44 Erk1  and the activation of Erk2 were normal (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <italic>c</italic> and <italic>d</italic>).  LPS stimulation of macrophages strongly activates not only  the Erk1/2 MAP kinases, but also the other two known  types of mammalian MAP kinases, p38 and JNK1/JNK2.  Enzymatic activation of JNK occurred normally in LPS-stimulated Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>a</italic>). Similarly, LPS- induced tyrosine phosphorylation of p38 occurred normally in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>b</italic>). Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking  also induced a modest increase in p38 immunoprecipitated  with antiphosphotyrosine antibodies from wild-type macrophages, although this response was less robust than was  the response seen with LPS (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>c</italic>). As was seen with  Erk1 and Erk2, the p38 response to Fc&#x003b3;R engagement was  largely absent in Syk-deficient macrophages. We did not  find JNK kinase activity increased in response to Fc&#x003b3;R  cross-linking in the fetal liver&#x02013;derived macrophages, or in  murine macrophage cell lines such as P388D1 and RAW  264.7 (data not shown). </p><p>As the activation of MAP kinases in response to LPS was  not affected by the absence of Syk, we next examined LPS-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of cellular proteins. We  did not observe any defects in LPS-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of the examined cellular substrates, including  Vav, Shc, and p145 <sup>Ship</sup> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Thus, Syk-deficient macrophages were not defective in any of the examined signaling responses to LPS. </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Fc&#x003b3;R Signaling Through Vav and p85 PI 3-Kinase in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup>  Macrophages.</title><p>We next examined the effect of loss of Syk  on Fc&#x003b3;R-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of Vav and of  the p85 subunit of PI 3-kinase. In normal macrophages,  p85 and Vav became immunoprecipitable with antiphosphotyrosine antibodies after Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>).  It is possible that the immunoprecipitated proteins were  themselves phosphorylated on tyrosine, or alternatively, that  they were precipitated by virtue of an association with another protein that was tyrosine phosphorylated upon cell  stimulation. Relatively harsh conditions were used for the  antiphosphotyrosine immunoprecipitations, so weak protein&#x02013; protein interactions were likely disrupted. In Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages, immunoprecipitation of Vav by antiphosphotyrosine antibodies was still induced by Fc&#x003b3;R stimulation,  but immunoprecipitation of p85 was abolished (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>).  Vav or its associated proteins may be substrates for members of the Src family of kinases that are associated with the  Fc&#x003b3;Rs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). The absence of p85 in antiphosphotyrosine  immunoprecipitates, however, suggested that signaling reactions involving PI 3-kinase were defective in Syk-deficient macrophages. </p><p>The perturbation of PI 3-kinase signaling in Syk-deficient  macrophages was particularly interesting as PI 3-kinase has  been implicated in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis in the human monocyte cell line U937 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>), and in murine bone  marrow&#x02013;derived macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>) by virtue of the blocking effect of a potent and selective inhibitor of PI 3-kinase,  wortmannin. We found that wortmannin also prevented  phagocytosis of EA by fetal liver&#x02013;derived cultured macrophages. This inhibitor did not affect Fc&#x003b3;R-induced polymerized actin accumulation around bound particles (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>), and thus blocked phagocytosis at a stage similar to the  block seen in Syk-deficient macrophages. In contrast to its  effects on Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis, wortmannin did  not affect macrophage phagocytosis of yeast, latex beads, or  <italic>E. coli</italic> (data not shown). </p></sec><sec disp-level="4"><title>Cytokine Production By Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> Macrophages.</title><p>Cross-linking of  Fc&#x003b3;R receptors on some macrophage populations can trigger the production and release of a variety of proinflammatory cytokines, bioactive lipids, and cytotoxic oxidants  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). The nature of the responses are dependent upon the  tissue origin of the macrophage, since different macrophage  types have distinctive properties in this regard. Unfortunately, cross-linking of Fc&#x003b3;Rs of fetal liver&#x02013;derived cultured  macrophages did not generate a respiratory burst in either  wild-type or Syk-deficient cells. Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking also  failed to trigger detectable production of TNF&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b2;, or  IL-6 (data not shown). In contrast, LPS caused these macrophages to release a number of proinflammatory mediators, including TNF&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6, and IL-12 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>).  LPS induction of TNF&#x003b1; release from Syk-deficient macrophages was indistinguishable from that induced from wild-type macrophages (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref> <italic>a</italic>). TNF&#x003b1; production during the  4 h after cell stimulation was no different in cells that were  or were not starved of the growth factors in L-Cell&#x02013;conditioned media before and during such short-term assays (data  not shown). Cell viability beyond 4 h could not be maintained without conditioned medium, however, so later times  were not tested in its absence. In addition, LPS-induced release of IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6, and IL-12 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>, <italic>b</italic> and <italic>c</italic>) were not  impaired in Syk-deficient macrophages. Thus, the signaling  pathways that are involved in production of proinflammatory cytokines by macrophages responding to LPS can  function independently of the Syk tyrosine kinase. </p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In prior experiments, we and others observed that stimulation of macrophages with LPS or Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking resulted in increased tyrosine phosphorylation and enzymatic  activation of Syk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). In this study, we have addressed the role of Syk in LPS- and Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated signaling events and in downstream biological events by examining these responses in vitro in cultured macrophages from  mice in which the gene for Syk had been deleted by gene  targeting. In each case examined, the responses of Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup>  macrophages to LPS were not different from the responses  of normal macrophages. These responses included early signaling events such as activation of the Erk1/2 and JNK  MAP kinases, and downstream events such as production  of the cytokines TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6, and IL-12. It is still  possible that Syk participates in one or more responses to  LPS that were not examined. Nonetheless, it is clear that  Syk does not play a central role in mediating many of the  LPS-triggered signaling events in macrophages. As tyrosine  kinase inhibitors block many LPS responses of macrophages  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>), it seems likely that tyrosine kinases other than Syk  play critical roles in mediating LPS responses.</p><p>In contrast to the normal LPS responses of Syk-deficient  macrophages, a number of Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated signaling events  were severely compromised, and Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis was completely blocked in these mutant macrophages.  Fc&#x003b3;R-triggered tyrosine phosphorylation of an array of cellular proteins, including Shc and p145<sup>Ship</sup>, was impaired in  Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages. Fc&#x003b3;R-triggered activation of Erk2 and  p38 MAP kinases was likewise impaired. Since the tyrosine  phosphorylation of Shc triggers its association with Grb-2  and SOS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>), which may lead to the activation of the  Ras&#x02013;Raf pathway, and subsequently to Erk1/2 MAP kinase activation, the defect in Erk2 activation in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells  may be attributable to deficient Shc-related signaling events.  Additionally, Syk appeared to be important for Fc&#x003b3;R- induced signaling events involving the p85 subunit of PI  3-kinase. In wild-type macrophages, stimulation through  the Fc&#x003b3;R resulted in increased quantities of this protein  and Vav in antiphosphotyrosine immunoprecipitates. In  Fc&#x003b3;R-stimulated Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells, increased amounts of Vav, but  not p85, were observed in antiphosphotyrosine immunoprecipitates. These results revealed an important role for Syk in  some, but not all Fc&#x003b3;R-induced signaling events.</p><p>Since Fc&#x003b3;Rs share subunits and ITAM signaling sequences with B and T cell antigen receptors and Fc&#x003b5;RI, the  importance of Syk for Fc&#x003b3;R signaling observed here is consistent with studies indicating a requirement for Syk or the  related tyrosine kinase in T cells, ZAP-70, for signaling by  these receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). Antigen or Fc receptor cross-linking triggers phosphorylation of receptor subunit ITAMs,  probably by different members of the Src family of kinases  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>), and subsequent recruitment of Syk or ZAP-70 tyrosine kinases to the phosphorylated ITAMs. It is currently  thought that Syk and ZAP-70 are then primarily responsible  for phosphorylation of important signaling targets. Given  the similarities of the lymphocyte antigen receptors and  Fc&#x003b3;Rs, it is likely that initiation of Fc&#x003b3;R signaling similarly  requires the sequential activity of these two families of tyrosine kinases. With this in mind, we examined Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated signaling events in macrophages genetically deficient for the three Src family members ordinarily expressed  in macrophages Hck, Fgr, and Lyn. We found that Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated Syk activation was impaired in Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup>  macrophages. This observation provides additional strong  evidence for a model of sequential activation of Src family  and Syk tyrosine kinases by the Fc&#x003b3;Rs.</p><p>In addition to its role in early signal transduction events,  Syk was also found to be absolutely required for Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis in macrophages. Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages  bound antibody-coated particles by their Fc&#x003b3;Rs, and initiated engulfment of the particles with actin-based cytoplasmic extensions. In the absence of Syk, however, the cells were  unable to internalize fully these antibody-coated particles.  Evidently, Syk was important for the Fc&#x003b3;R-triggered cellular events necessary to extend further and fuse the leading  edge of the macrophage membrane that surrounded the particle. These results are in agreement with findings demonstrating a role for Syk in FcR-mediated phagocytosis in various artificial systems. For example, coexpression of Syk  in COS-1 transfectants expressing Fc&#x003b3;Rs promoted efficient Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), and chimeric transmembrane proteins containing Syk kinase domains were  capable of triggering phagocytosis by COS-1 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). In  the latter case, the kinase activity of Syk was sufficient and  necessary to trigger phagocytosis in COS cells. Interestingly, we found that Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis was  only delayed in Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages, despite severely diminished Syk activation. Evidently, the reduced  number of activated Syk molecules clustered beneath cross-linked Fc&#x003b3;Rs in Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages were still  sufficient to allow phagocytosis to proceed with only a  moderate delay.</p><p>The phagocytic defect in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages may reflect  the lack of Syk kinase action needed to activate signaling  pathways necessary for Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis, as suggested by experiments in Cos-1 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Alternatively,  the physical association of Syk with phosphorylated receptor tails may allow it to serve an adaptor-type function at  cross-linked receptors to allow recruitment of other important proteins to the site of particle binding. Chacko et. al  have described such a role for Syk in Fc&#x003b3;RII signaling in  platelets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). In any case, the experiments reported here  demonstrate that Syk is a crucial element in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis by cells in which it is a naturally occurring and biologically important response after cross-linking  of these receptors. Importantly, the phagocytic defect in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup>  macrophages was limited to phagocytosis via activated Fc&#x003b3;Rs.  Phagocytosis of microorganisms and synthetic particles was  unaffected by the absence of Syk. Interesting in this regard  are observations indicating that there are distinct cytoskeletal structures involved in phagocytosis of particles bound to  different receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>).</p><p>Several Fc&#x003b3;R-induced signaling events have been implicated as participating in phagocytosis. Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking  triggers phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> activation and subsequent arachidonic acid (AA) release, and it was found that the AA was a  critical component in phagocytosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). In those studies, a  block in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis was overcome by  providing exogenous AA in the culture media. The phagocytic defect in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages was not remedied by addition of exogenous AA (data not shown). It is still possible  that local production of AA plays an important role in  Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis, but that this is only one of  several required Syk-dependent signaling events.</p><p>Another signal transduction protein implicated in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis is PI 3-kinase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Fc&#x003b3;R engagement  induced an increase in p85 protein immunoprecipitable by  antiphosphotyrosine antibodies in normal macrophages, but  not in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages. Moreover, we noted a striking  similarity between the phagocytic defect in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells, and  the stage at which phagocytosis was blocked by treatment  of normal cells with the PI 3-kinase inhibitor wortmannin.  In both cases, actin cups formed, but could not close off to  internalize the bound particle (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>). In agreement  with our results, another group has recently reported that  wortmannin blocks phagocytosis at this stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Thus, it  is attractive to propose that the defect in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages  results from a failure to activate a signaling pathway involving PI 3-kinase. Syk may be required to activate and/or to  properly localize PI 3-kinase activity during phagocytosis.  Interesting in this regard is the observation that Fc&#x003b3;RII  cross-linking on platelets induced the association of the  Fc&#x003b3;RII with PI 3-kinase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>).</p><p>It should be noted that Fc&#x003b3;R signaling in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages also showed a defect in a second signaling component that acts on inositol-containing phospholipids,  p145<sup>Ship</sup>. This molecule is an inositol phosphatase that hydrolyzes the 5-phosphate of phosphatidylinositol (3,4,5)P<sub>3</sub>,  the product of PI 3-kinase, to generate phosphatidylinositol  (3,4)P<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>). It is not known how the activity of  p145<sup>Ship</sup> is regulated, but Fc&#x003b3;R engagement leads to tyrosine phosphorylation of p145<sup>Ship</sup> and its association with  both Syk and Shc (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). These signaling events were also  defective in the Syk-deficient macrophages, and thus,  p145<sup>Ship</sup> function is also likely to be impaired in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells  stimulated via Fc&#x003b3;R cross-linking.</p><p>How PI 3-kinase and/or p145<sup>Ship</sup> may be acting in the  phagocytic process is of course not known. One possibility  is suggested by the connection between PI 3-kinase and  small G proteins involved in cytoskeletal rearrangements.  The Rho family GTPases Rho, Rac, and CDC42 play important roles in the regulation of the actin cytoskeleton to  produce membrane ruffling, filopodia, and lamellipodia  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>), and likely play an important role in phagocytosis. PI  3-kinase is thought to play a role in coordinating these responses. For example, activation of Rac via the PDGF receptor requires synthesis of PI 3-kinase phosphoinositide  products and association of PI 3-kinase with receptor cytoplasmic domains, indicating that PI 3-kinase can act upstream of Rac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). Similarly, inhibitors of PI 3-kinase prevent agonist-stimulated guanine nucleotide exchange on  Rac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>).</p><p>The phagocytic process may be analogous to other processes that require the combined activities of Rho-family  proteins. Nobes et al. concluded that stimulation of CDC42  induced the formation of filopodia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). CDC42 also can  stimulate Rac, which in turn initiates a process whereby the  filopodia are filled in by advancing lamella. This process  may be related to the events in Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis. That is, the phagocytic cup may be a scaffold of filopodia-like structures. The formation of actin cups may be followed by filling in over the cup by advancing lamellipodia.  According to this hypothesis, a key issue is how the activities of Rho-family members are orchestrated to allow phagocytosis to proceed successfully. The final events in phagocytosis may be defective in Syk-deficient macrophages  because signaling events, perhaps involving Rho family  proteins, PI 3-kinase, and p145<sup>Ship</sup>, are not activated or localized properly in the absence of Syk.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Binding and phagocytosis of antibody-coated EA by wild-type, Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, and Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup>  macrophages. Adherent wild-type,  Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, and Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages (<italic>a</italic>, left to right) were incubated  with EA (10<sup>7</sup> cells per ml) for 30 min  at 37&#x000b0;C before removal of unbound  EA. Uninternalized EA were lysed in  <italic>b&#x02013;f.</italic> All normal macrophages (<italic>b</italic> and  <italic>e</italic>) and Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup>macrophages  (<italic>c</italic>) contained many internalized  erythrocytes. The large load of ingested material resulted in a loss of  cell body extensions, and a more  rounded appearance of the macrophages. None of the Syk-deficient  macrophages contained any internalized erythrocytes (<italic>d</italic> and <italic>f</italic>&#x02009;&#x02009;&#x02009;). These  macrophages had a frilled appearance  due to the interlacing of actin-rich  macrophage cell membrane structures around each bound erythrocyte. Bar, 10 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Greatly decreased Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated Syk activation in Hck<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/ Fgr<sup>&#x02212;</sup>/Lyn<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages. Bone marrow&#x02013;derived macrophages were incubated with growth media (0&#x02032;) or anti-Fc&#x003b3;R mAb 2.4G2 followed by  anti&#x02013;rat IgG cross-linking for the indicated times. The protein kinase activity of Syk was assessed by in vitro autophosphorylation of immunoprecipitated Syk followed by SDS-PAGE and autoradiography (<italic>a</italic>). Anti-Syk  immunoblotting (<italic>b</italic>) showed that equivalent amounts of Syk protein were  present in each reaction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Formation of actin-rich membrane cups around bound EA in normal and Syk-deficient macrophages. Macrophages were incubated with EA  on ice for 20 min. Fixed and permeabilized normal (<italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic>) and Syk-deficient (<italic>c</italic> and <italic>d</italic>) cells were stained with Oregon green&#x02013;phalloidin to visualize  F-actin. The bound erythrocytes are apparent under phase microscopy (<italic>a</italic> and <italic>c</italic>). Corresponding actin-lined cups visible by fluorescence microscopy (<italic>b</italic>  and <italic>d</italic>) are evident. Alternatively, after incubation on ice, cells were washed and further incubated for 20 min at 37&#x000b0;C, during which time there was dissolution of actin cup structures in Syk-deficient macrophages (<italic>g</italic> and <italic>h</italic>) as well as internalization of the EA in the case of normal cells (<italic>e</italic> and <italic>f</italic>&#x02009;&#x02009;&#x02009;). Several internalized EA (*) and bound, noninternalized EA (o) are indicated by symbols inside the erythrocytes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f3a"/><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f3e"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Impaired Fc&#x003b3;R-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of cellular  substrates in Syk-deficient macrophages. Cells were incubated with growth  media (0&#x02032;) or anti-Fc&#x003b3;R mAb 2.4G2 followed by anti&#x02013;rat IgG cross-linking for the indicated times. Cells were lysed, and were subjected to SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting with antiphosphotyrosine antibodies (<italic>a</italic>). The  molecular mass (in kD) of markers and the positions of major phosphotyrosine-containing proteins are indicated at the right and left of <italic>a</italic>, respectively. Alternatively, cell lysates were subjected to immunoprecipitation  with anti-Shc antibodies (<italic>b</italic>) or anti-Erk2 antibodies (<italic>c</italic>). Erk2, Shc, and  Shc-associated proteins were resolved by SDS-PAGE, and their phosphorylation status was determined by immunoblotting with antiphosphotyrosine antibodies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Impaired Fc&#x003b3;R-induced MAPK activation in Syk-deficient  macrophages. Wild-type and mutant macrophages were incubated with  growth media (0&#x02032;) or with anti-Fc&#x003b3;R mAb 2.4G2, followed by cross-linking with anti&#x02013;rat IgG for the indicated times. The electrophoretic mobility shift of p44 MAP kinase was assessed by SDS-PAGE, and by immunoblotting with anti-MAP kinase antibodies (<italic>a</italic>). Alternatively, Erk1 and  Erk2 activity was assessed directly by immunoprecipitation with anti-Erk2  antibodies and measurement of the ability to phosphorylate the substrate  myelin basic protein in vitro (<italic>b</italic> and <italic>d</italic>). Unstimulated or Fc&#x003b3;R-stimulated  wild-type (<italic>stippled bars</italic>) or Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<italic>black bars</italic>) macrophages were tested (<italic>b</italic>).  Values shown represent <sup>33</sup>PO<sub>4</sub> incorporation from labeled ATP into the  substrate protein. Seven separate experiments using Syk-deficient cells  gave similar results. LPS-induced mobility shift of Erk1 (<italic>c</italic>) and enzymatic  activation of Erk2 (<italic>d</italic>) was also assessed in wild-type (<italic>stippled bars</italic>), or Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup>  (<italic>black bars</italic>) macrophages exposed to 1 &#x003bc;g/ml LPS for the indicated times.  Similar results were obtained in seven separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Activation of JNK and tyrosine phosphorylation of p38 in  Fc&#x003b3;R-stimulated and LPS-activated macrophages. Activation of JNK in  wild-type (<italic>stippled bars</italic>), or Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<italic>black bars)</italic> macrophages exposed to 1  &#x003bc;g/ml LPS for the indicated times was assessed by immunoprecipitation  with anti-JNK antibodies, followed by in vitro phosphorylation of a c-Jun&#x02013; GST fusion protein substrate (<italic>a</italic>). For analysis of p38 phosphorylation,  phosphotyrosine-containing proteins were immunoprecipitated from lysates of unstimulated (0&#x02032;), LPS-stimulated (<italic>b</italic>), or Fc&#x003b3;R-activated (c) macrophages. Proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose, and the region containing p38 was probed with anti-p38  antibody. Similar results were obtained in three experiments comparing  Syk-deficient and normal macrophages.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f6"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Lack of defect in LPS-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of  cellular substrates in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> macrophages. Cells were incubated with media  or media plus 1 &#x003bc;g/ml LPS for the indicated times. Cells were lysed, and  the lysate proteins were subjected to SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting  with antiphosphotyrosine antibody (<italic>a</italic>). Molecular mass markers (in kD)  and major phosphotyrosine-containing substrates are indicated on the right  and the left of <italic>a</italic>, respectively. The Erk2 MAPK band, as confirmed by  subsequent immunoblotting with anti-Erk2 antibodies (not shown), is indicated as p42. Alternatively, cell lysates were subject to immunoprecipitation with anti-Shc antibodies (<italic>b</italic>) and immunoblotting with antiphosphotyrosine antibody, or to immunoprecipitation with antiphosphotyrosine  antibody and immunoblotting with anti-Vav (<italic>c</italic>) antibodies. The positions  of proteins of interest are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f7"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Altered Fc&#x003b3;R-induced signaling events associated with p85  PI 3-kinase, but not with Vav in Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells. Fetal liver&#x02013;derived macrophage cultures were stimulated through their Fc&#x003b3;R for 5 min. Cellular  lysate proteins were immunoprecipitated with antiphosphotyrosine antibodies, and the immunoprecipitated proteins were subjected to SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting with anti-Vav and anti-p85 PI 3-kinase antibodies as indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f8"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Effect of the PI 3-kinase inhibitor wortmannin on Fc&#x003b3;R-mediated phagocytosis and actin-based phagocytic cup formation. Macrophages grown on coverslips were pretreated with wortmannin (50 nM),  for 20 min, and were then incubated with EA either for 20 min on ice to  obtain stable actin-lined phagocytic cups (<italic>a</italic>), or at 37&#x000b0;C for 40 min, after  which time bound, but not internalized erythrocytes were lysed with  1.44% NH<sub>4</sub>Cl (<italic>b</italic>). Fixed and permeabilized cells were stained with BODIPY-phalloidin, and were examined by phase microscopy (<italic>a</italic>) or by fluorescence microscopy to visualize F-actin (<italic>b</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f9"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Production and release of inflammatory cytokines in Syk-deficient and wild-type macrophages responding to LPS. Syk<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (&#x02022;) or  wild-type (&#x025cb;) cultured macrophages were stimulated with 50 ng/ml LPS  for the time indicated, and concentrations of TNF-&#x003b1; (<italic>a</italic>), IL-1&#x003b2; (<italic>b</italic>, <italic>solid  line</italic>), IL-6 (<italic>b</italic>, <italic>dashed line</italic>), IL-12 (<italic>c</italic>, <italic>solid line</italic>), or IL-12 from &#x003b3;-IFN (100  U/ml) primed macrophages (<italic>c</italic>, <italic>dashed line</italic>) were determined by ELISA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM.970128f10"/></fig></sec><ack><p>We thank Drs. Vivien Chan, Julie Hambleton, Stacey Harmer, James Richards, and Steven Weinstein, for  many helpful discussions and for critical reading of the manuscript.</p><p>This work was supported by grants AI20038 and AI33442 from the U.S. National Institutes of Health. M.T.  Crowley was supported by National Institutes of Health training grant T32AI07334. P.S. Costello and V.  Tybulewicz were supported in part by the Medical Research Council and the Imperial Cancer Research  Fund, and by grants from the Oiver Bird Fund (V. Tybulewicz) and the Leukaemia Research Fund (V. Tybulewicz).</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinet</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fc receptors</article-title><source>Ann Rev  Immunol</source><year>1991</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1910686</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fc receptor signaling</article-title><source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7887303</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sylvestre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Clynes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FcR gamma chain deletion results in pleiotrophic effector cell defects</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313472</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hikida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohmori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Augmented humoral and anaphylactic responses in Fc gamma RII-deficient mice</article-title><source>Nature (Lond)</source><year>1996</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8552190</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fc receptors: rubor redux</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8069908</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stockinger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capacity of antigen uptake by B cells, fibroblasts or macrophages determines efficiency of presentation of a soluble self antigen (C5) to T lymphocytes</article-title><source>Eur J  Immunol</source><year>1992</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1271</fpage><lpage>1278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1577067</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation is required for Fc receptor-mediated phagocytosis in mouse macrophages</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1993</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7678851</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Indik</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular dissection of Fc&#x003b3; receptor mediated phagocytosis</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1995</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>4389</fpage><lpage>4399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8541526</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Floto</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fc gamma receptor-mediated phagocytosis requires tyrosine kinase activity and is ligand independent</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>1995</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7875211</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiener</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkhardt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schieven</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolen</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledbetter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-linking of Fc gamma receptor I (Fc gamma RI) and receptor II (Fc gamma RII) on monocytic cells activates a signal transduction pathway common to both Fc receptors that involves the stimulation of p72 Syk protein tyrosine kinase</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>24442</fpage><lpage>24448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8226994</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durden</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein-tyrosine kinase p72syk in Fc gamma RI receptor signaling</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1994</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>2102</fpage><lpage>2108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7522622</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darby</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Geahlen</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of macrophage Fc gamma RIIIA activates the receptor-associated protein tyrosine kinase Syk and induces phosphorylation of multiple proteins including p95Vav and p62/GAP-associated protein</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1994</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>5429</fpage><lpage>5437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8189062</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Seed</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clustered syk tyrosine kinase domains trigger phagocytosis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1103</fpage><lpage>1107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8577722</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFranco</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of protein tyrosine phosphorylation by the B-lymphocyte antigen receptor</article-title><source>Nature (Lond)</source><year>1990</year><volume>345</volume><fpage>810</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1694265</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hourihane</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFranco</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuuchi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstitution of B cell antigen receptor-induced signaling events in a nonlymphoid cell line by expressing the Syk protein-tyrosine kinase</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>6458</fpage><lpage>6466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8626447</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hambleton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFranco</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of c-Jun N-terminal kinase in bacterial lipopolysaccharide-stimulated macrophages</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad  Sci USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>2774</fpage><lpage>2778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8610116</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mee</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duddy</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlong</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Geahlen</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tybulewicz</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perinatal lethality and blocked B-cell development in mice lacking the tyrosine kinase Syk</article-title><source>Nature  (Lond)</source><year>1995</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7477352</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipopolysaccharide (LPS)- induced macrophage activation and signal transduction in the absence of Src-family kinases Hck, Fgr, and Lyn</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>1661</fpage><lpage>1670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9151903</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFranco</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation-induced association of a 145-kDa tyrosine-phosphorylated protein with shc and syk in B lymphocytes and macrophages</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>1145</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8557643</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeFranco</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transmembrane signaling by antigen receptors of B and T lymphocytes</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>175</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Oers</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Killeen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lck regulates the tyrosine phosphorylation of the T cell receptor subunits and ZAP-70 in murine thymocytes</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1996</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8642247</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bewarder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinrich</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Flaswinkel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Reth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo and in vitro specificity of protein tyrosine kinases for immunoglobulin G receptor (Fc gamma RII) phosphorylation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>4735</fpage><lpage>4743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8756631</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleiman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hippen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylated immunoreceptor signaling motifs (ITAMs) exhibit unique abilities to bind and activate Lyn and Syk tyrosine kinases</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1995</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>4596</fpage><lpage>4603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7594458</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gbarah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lectinophagocytosis of type 1 fimbriated (mannose-specific) <italic>Escherichia  coli</italic>in the mouse peritoneum</article-title><source>J Leukocyte Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1355788</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekizawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohrui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic motility reflects phagocytic activity in alveolar macrophages from dog lungs</article-title><source>Respir Physiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8570922</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuijnman</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Capel</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Winkel</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human low-affinity IgG receptor Fc gamma RIIa (CD32) introduced into mouse fibroblasts mediates phagocytosis of sensitized erythrocytes</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1992</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1651</fpage><lpage>1656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1532752</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulbins</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monocyte deactivation by interleukin 10 via inhibition of tyrosine kinase activity and the Ras signaling pathway</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad  Sci USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>8602</fpage><lpage>8606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8078929</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ninomiya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazeki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazeki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase in Fc gamma receptor signaling</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>22732</fpage><lpage>22737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7521331</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for phosphoinositied 3-kinase in the completion of macropinocytosis and phagocytosis by macrophages</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>1249</fpage><lpage>1260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8947549</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signal transduction mechanisms through Fc gamma receptors on the mouse macrophage surface</article-title><source>FASEB  J</source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1706281</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation of the gamma subunit of Fc gamma receptors, p72syk, and paxillin during Fc receptor-mediated phagocytosis in macrophages</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>3897</fpage><lpage>3902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7508923</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFranco</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial lipopolysaccharide stimulates protein tyrosine phosphorylation in macrophages</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1991</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>4148</fpage><lpage>4152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1709735</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Takashiba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Amar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of protein kinase C and protein tyrosine kinase in lipopolysaccharide-induced TNF- alpha and IL-1 beta production by human monocytes</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1994</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>1818</fpage><lpage>1824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7519214</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chanmugam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beppu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radicicol, a protein tyrosine kinase inhibitor, suppresses the expression of mitogen-inducible cyclooxygenase in macrophages stimulated with lipopolysaccharide and in experimental glomerulonephritis</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>5418</fpage><lpage>5426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7890656</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downward</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The GRB2/Sem-5 adaptor protein</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1994</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8307166</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>PST</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Downward</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tybulewicz</surname><given-names>VLJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critical role for the tyrosine kinase Syk in signalling through the high affinity IgE receptor of mast cells</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1996</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2595</fpage><lpage>2605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9000133</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazer</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadlecek</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Absence of ZAP-70 prevents signaling through the antigen receptor on peripheral blood T cells but not on thymocytes</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7561679</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roifman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mutation in zap-70 protein tyrosine kinase results in a selective immunodeficiency</article-title><source>J Clin Immunol</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Inazu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Homma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nukada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurosaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine kinases Lyn and Syk regulate B cell receptor-coupled Ca2<sub>&#x0002b;</sub>mobilization through distinct pathways</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1994</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1341</fpage><lpage>1349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8137818</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keegan</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multichain immune recognition receptors: similarities in structure and signaling pathways</article-title><source>Immunol Today</source><year>1992</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1575894</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reif</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The protein interactions of the immunoglobulin receptor family tyrosine-based activation motifs present in the T cell receptor zeta subunits and the CD3 gamma, delta and epsilon chains</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>1068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8647168</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chacko</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Coggeshall</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphoinositide 3-kinase and p72syk noncovalently associate with the low affinity Fc gamma receptor on human platelets through an immunoreceptor tyrosine-based activation motif. Reconstitution with synthetic phosphopeptides</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>10775</fpage><lpage>10781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8631888</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Aderem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular definition of distinct cytoskeletal structures involved in complement- and Fc receptor-mediated phagocytosis in macrophages</article-title><source>J Exp  Med</source><year>1996</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8760816</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lennartz</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arachidonic acid is essential for IgG Fc receptor-mediated phagocytosis by human monocytes</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1991</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1830070</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosten</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Majerus</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Krystal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 145-kDa protein induced to associate with Shc by multiple cytokines is an inositol tetraphosphate and phosphatidylinositol 3,4,5-triphosphate 5-phosphatase</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1689</fpage><lpage>1693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8643691</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lioubin</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Algate</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aebersold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohrschneider</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p150Ship, a signal transduction molecule with inositol polyphosphate-5-phosphatase activity</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1996</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1084</fpage><lpage>1095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8654924</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nobes</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rho, rac, and cdc42 GTPases regulate the assembly of multimolecular focal complexes associated with actin stress fibers, lamellipodia, and filopodia</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7536630</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguinoa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokoe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wennstrom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Claesson-Welsh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Symons</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PDGF stimulates an increase in GTP-Rac via activation of phosphoinositide 3-kinase</article-title><source>Curr  Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7627555</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguinoa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A heterotrimeric GTPase-regulated isoform of PI3K and the regulation of its potential effectors</article-title><source>Philos Trans R  Soc Lond Ser B Biol Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8650268</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><label>1</label><p><italic>Abbreviations used in this paper:</italic> AA, arachidonic acid; EA, erythrocytes  coated with antibody; Fc&#x003b3;R, Fc receptor for IgG; GST, glutathione  S-transferase; GST&#x02013;c-Jun, GST fused to the NH<sub>2</sub> terminus of c-Jun;  ITAM, immunoreceptor tyrosine-based activation motif; JNK, Jun NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal kinase; LCM, L cell conditioned media; Pl, phosphatidylinositol.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>


